Francis Davis Millet and Millet Family
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Letters, 1867-1915, undated, Series 3:; (Boxes 1-2; 0.5 linear ft.; Reel 5904)
  - F. D. Millet (Reel 5904)
    - Collected Letters from John Singer Sargent, 1887 and circa 1887 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Letters about the Grange, 1879-1897, undated (Reel 5904, Frame 432-508)
  - Kathleen Millet (sister) to Margherita, 1878-1879 (Reel 5904, Frame 509-523)
  - Lily Millet (wife) (Reel 5904)
    - Letters, 1885-1915, undated (Reel 5904, Frame 524-624)
    - Letters of Condolence, 1912, (3 folders) (Reel 5904, Frame 625-853)
  - From Lucia Millet (sister) to Family, 1882-1886, undated, (6 folders) (Reel 5904, Frame 855-1176)
- Notes and Writings, circa 1891-1970, undated, Series 4:; (Box 3; 1.0 linear ft.; Reels 5904-5906)
  Millet's murals and paintings were noted for the historical accuracy of their costumes and period details. Many of the notes from his extensive research are recorded in eleven undated copybooks, titled for easy reference. Additional volumes of notes by Millet concern 17th century Italian art, Bulgarian history and costume (probably from his student days in Antwerp since it is in French), and the Philippines, compiled circa 1898-1899.
  Writings by Millet consist of manuscripts of published and unpublished articles and short stories, and texts of lectures and speeches. Writings about Millet are by relatives. "Frank D. Millet: A Versatile American," by niece Hilda Millet Booth and son John A. P. Millet, is accompanied by notes, drafts, and related correspondence. "In Search of an Ancestor," by granddaughter Joyce A. Sharpey-Schafer, was published in 1984 as Frank D. Millet: Soldier of Fortune, 1846-1912. A copy of the book is included with Series 6.
  This series is arranged into 4 subseries:
  4.1: Notes by F. D. Millet, 1872-circa 1899, undated
  4.2: Writings by F. D. Millet, circa 1891-1910, undated
  4.3: Writings about F. D. Millet, 1915 -1966, undated
  4.4: Miscellaneous Writings, 1937
  - Notes by F. D. Millet, 1872-circa 1899, undated, 4.1:
    - Reference Notes (Reel 5904)
      - Arms and Armory, undated (Reel 5904, Frame 1180-1232)
      - Greek Costume: Archaic, Doric, Ionic; Greek Costume, undated, (2 volumes) (Reel 5904, Frame 1233-1259)
    - Military Costume, Crowns and Decorations, Gladiators, undated (Reel 5904, Frame 1260-1267)
    - Military Costume, Crowns and Decorations, Gladiators, undated (Reel 5905, Frame 14-61)
    - The Poenula, Head and Foot Gear, Leg Covering, Toilette, Ornaments, undated (Reel 5905, Frame 62-93)
    - Religion, undated (Reel 5905, Frame 94-126)
    - Roman Costume; Costume of Women, Roman; Costume Notes; The Toga and its Variations, undated, (4 volumes) (Reel 5905, Frame 127-261)
    - The Tunic, undated (Reel 5905, Frame 262-282)
    - Student Notes, "L'art italien au 17 siècle;" "History and Costume" of Bulgaria, 1871-1872, (1 volume in French) (Reel 5905, Frame 283-335)
    - Notes on the Philippines, etc., circa 1898-1899 (Reel 5905, Frame 336-373)
  - Writings by F. D. Millet, circa 1891-1910, undated, 4.2:
    - Article and Short Stories (Reel 5905)
      - "A Balkan Bivouac," undated (Reel 5905, Frame 375-385)
      - "Benozzo Gozzoli," undated (Reel 5905, Frame 386-416)
      - "Dash Across the Line," undated (Reel 5905, Frame 417-441)
      - "The Expedition to the Philippines," circa 1898-1899, (3 folders) (Reel 5905, Frame 442-848)
      - "Fifteen Minutes with an American Lady" and "Seven Minutes with an American Lady," undated (Reel 5905, Frame 849-858)
      - "From Plevna to Constantinople," undated (Reel 5905, Frame 859-900)
      - "From the Black Forest to the Black Sea," circa 1891-1893 (Reel 5905, Frame 901-1014)
      - "A Malay Monte Carlo," undated (Reel 5905, Frame 1015-1029)
      - "A Moment in a Hostile Bivouac," undated (Reel 5905, Frame 1030-1041)
      - "Mrs. Burden's Baby," undated (Reel 5905, Frame 1042-1072)
      - Untitled, undated, (2 manuscripts) (Reel 5905, Frame 1073-1104)
    - Lectures and Speeches (Reel 5905)
      - "War Correspondence," Buffalo Club, April 23, 1904 (Reel 5905, Frame 1105-1148)
      - "Conditions and Possibilities of Art in the United States," Yale University, June 1, 1904 (Reel 5905, Frame 1149-1213)
      - "The American Federation of Arts," The Washington Society of The Fine Arts, Continental Hall, May 4, 1910 (Reel 5905, Frame 1214-1221)
  - Writings About F. D. Millet, 1915 -1966, undated, 4.3:
    - Hilda Millet Booth and John [Albert] Parsons Millet, "Frank Millet: A Versatile American" (Reel 5905)
      - Correspondence, 1915-1970, undated, (7 folders) (Reel 5905, Frame 1223-1447)
      - Correspondence, 1915-1970, undated, (7 folders) (Reel 5906, Frame 14-413)
      - Manuscript, 1939, (5 folders) (Reel 5906, Frame 414-785)
      - Early Drafts and Notes, circa 1934-1939, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 37-40)
      - Early Drafts and Notes, circa 1934-1939, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 41-44)
      - Miscellaneous Notes, circa 1934-1939 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Francis Davis Millet, "Frank Millet, A Sketch" (the author is the grandson of F. D. Millet; also on reel 848), circa 1940 (Reel 5906, Frame 788-853)
    - John A. P. Millet, "Frank D. Millet: A New England Artist in His Rural Studio, His Career as a Journalist and Painter, His Accomplishments and Surroundings" (the author is the son of F. D. Millet), undated (Reel 5906, Frame 854-860)
    - J[osiah] B. Millet, "Recollections," a Biographical Essay about Asa Millet (the author is the the brother of F. D. Millet), undated (Reel 5906, Frame 861-879)
    - Joyce A. Sharpey-Schafer, "In Search of an Ancestor," 1966 (Reel 5906, Frame 880-967)
  - Miscellaneous Writings, 1937, 4.4:
    - John A. P. Millet, Untitled Manuscript about Psychology (the author is the son of F. D. Millet), 1937 (Box 3, Folder 50)
- Art Work, 1872-1908, undated, Series 5:; (Box 4; 0.5 linear ft.; Reels 5906-5907)
  Art work by Millet includes twelve sketchbooks, containing pencil sketches, a few finished drawings, and a small number of ink drawings. The sketchbooks were executed over a quarter of a century, from his student days in Antwerp through 1896, mostly during periods of travel. Subjects, many of which are identified, include landscapes, buildings, and local peoples with emphasis on their clothing. Loose sketches and drawings, 1872-1874 and undated, record Millet's travels are arranged by location. Two watercolors are "Menu, Nov. 14th, Peking" with a finished painting of a hillside pagoda by the water, on board; and a small sketch of a man and boy, on paper.
  Work by other artists includes 20 caricatures drawn in ink, several of which are annotated by John Singer Sargent. Sargent experts Richard Ormond and Stanley Olson, in 1985 correspondence with the Archives of American Art attribute the caricatures to Sargent. Depicted are Sargent, Edwin Austin Abbey, Lily and Frank Millet, Mrs. Gosse, Mrs. Alma-Tadema [?], Mrs. Blashfield [?], and unidentified tennis players.
  The series is arranged into 2 subseries:
  5.1: By F. D. Millet, 1872-1908, undated
  5.2: By Other Artists, circa 1885-1886, undated
  - By F. D. Millet, 1872-1908, undated, 5.1:
    - Sketchbooks (Reel 5906)
      - Holland; Vol. 2: Italy, undated, (2 volumes) (Reel 5906, Frame 972-1057)
      - "E.A.A.," (probably United States), undated (Reel 5906, Frame 1058-1078)
      - Belgium, Austria, and Germany, 1872-1873 (Reel 5906, Frame 1079-1107)
      - Turkey, Russia, Romania; Turkey and Greece, 1873-1874, (2 volumes) (Reel 5906, Frame 1108-1203)
      - Russo-Turkish War, 1877-1878 (Reel 5906, Frame 1204-1280)
        (includes notes in English and Russian)
      - The Danube, circa 1891, (4 volumes) (Reel 5906, Frame 1281-1485)
      - "Algiers," (includes Tripoli and Tunisia), 1896 (Reel 5907, Frame 14-56)
    - Loose Sketches and Drawings (Reel 5907)
      - Antwerp Sketches, undated (Reel 5907, Frame 57-68)
      - Bulgaria, undated (Reel 5907, Frame 69-72)
      - England, 1872, undated (Reel 5907, Frame 73-90)
      - Germany, undated (Reel 5907, Frame 91-92)
      - Italy, 1874, undated (Reel 5907, Frame 93-101)
      - Romania, 1872 (Reel 5907, Frame 102-103)
      - Turkey, undated (Reel 5907, Frame 104-106)
      - Unidentified, undated (Reel 5907, Frame 107-111)
    - Watercolors, 1908, undated (Reel 5907, Frame 112-115)
  - By Other Artists, circa 1885-1886, undated, 5.2:
    - Unidentified Artists, undated, (1 pencil drawing, and 1 ink drawing) (Reel 5907, Frame 116-118)
    - John Singer Sargent, circa 1885-1886, undated, (20 caricatures) (Reel 5907, Frame 119-134)
- Printed Matter, 1764-1984, undated, Series 6:; (Box 4; 0.25 linear ft.; Reel 5907)
  Among the printed matter are newspaper articles by F. D. Millet, along with clippings about or mentioning him, reproductions, exhibition catalogs and announcements. Of interest are Vienna Exposition memorabilia, and a full length biography, Soldier of Fortune: F. D. Millet, 1846-1912 by granddaughter Joyce A. Sharpey-Schafer.
  Printed matter about the Abbot's Grange, used by Millet and his associates as their Broadway studio, is filed with Series 5. A copy of "In Search of an Ancestor," the manuscript for Joyce A. Sharpey-Schafer's book Soldier of Fortune: F. D. Millet, 1846-1912 is included with other writings in Series 4.
  - Articles About or Mentioning F. D. Millet, 1872-1934, undated (Reel 5907, Frame 136-170)
  - Articles by F. D. Millet, 1877-1896 (Reel 5907, Frame 171-225)
  - Auction Catalogue, Parke-Bernet Galleries, Inc., March 7, 1940 (Reel 5907, Frame 226-228)
  - Exhibition Catalogs and Announcements, 1876-1971 (Reel 5907, Frame 229-236)
  - Miscellaneous Items, 1875, undated (Reel 5907, Frame 237-241)
  - Newspaper Clipping about Russian General Joseph Gurkow, undated (Reel 5907, Frame 242-243)
  - Newspapers (item dated 1723 is a facsimile; not microfilmed), 1764-1807 (Reel 5907)
  - Reproductions of Illustrations by E. A. Abbey, F. S. Gifford, and C.K.S., undated (Reel 5907, Frame 245-260)
  - Reproductions of Works by F. D. Millet, undated (Reel 5907, Frame 261-274)
  - Soldier of Fortune: F. D. Millet, 1846-1912 by Joyce A. Sharpey-Schafer, 1984 (Reel 5907, Frame 275-373)
  - The Story of an Old English Hostelry by S. B. Russell (about the Lygon Arms in Broadway), 1914 (Reel 5907, Frame unfilmed)
  - Vienna Exposition Memorabilia, 1873 (Reel 5907, Frame 375-417)
  - The Young Ladies' Assistant in Drawing and Painting by Maria Turner, 1833 (Reel 5907, Frame unfilmed)
- Miscellaneous Records, 1725-1897, undated, Series 7:; (Box 4; 7 folders; Reel 5907)
  Material about the Abbot's Grange, which served as Millet's studio, may have been compiled preparatory to restoration of the structure. Series 3 includes letters concerning its purchase and restoration.
  - Currency, 1785-1851, undated (Reel 5907, Frame unfilmed)
  - "The Grange" (Reel 5907)
    - Drawings, Sketches, Notes re: Architectural Details, undated (Reel 5907, Frame 421-466)
    - Maps, undated (Reel 5907, Frame 467-470)
    - Miscellaneous Notes, undated (Reel 5907, Frame 471-480)
    - Printed Matter, 1819-1895, undated (Reel 5907, Frame 481-518)
  - Photographs, circa 1896-1897 (Reel 5907, Frame 519-523)
  - Legal Documents, 1725-1739 (Reel 5907, Frame 524-527)
- Photographs, circa 1872-circa 1910, undated, Series 8:; (Box 4; 7 folders; Reels 5907)
  Among the photographs of people are portraits of Millet, as well as pictures of Millet and wife, Lily, with their children. Also included are photographs of Mary Anderson, Asa Millet with granddaughter Kate, and F. D. and Lily Millet with Charles F. Adams, Jr. Photographs of works of art primarily depict paintings by Millet. In addition there are photographs of drawings by other artists that appeared in Puck magazine, circa 1897-1898. Photographs of Millet's Broadway studio, the Abbot's Grange, are filed with Series 7. See related microfilmed collections of loaned materials, on reels 849 and 1080, for additional photographs of family and the Millet's Russell House.
  8.1: People, circa 1872-circa 1910
  8.2: Works of Art, circa 1897-1898, undated
  - People, circa 1872-circa 1910, 8.1:
    - Mary Anderson as "Galatea," (inscribed "To Jack from his loving friend Mary de Navarro, 1894"), circa 1894 (Reel 5907, Frame 530-531)
    - Asa Millet and Granddaughter Kate, circa 1883 (Reel 5907, Frame 532-534)
    - F. D. Millet (carte de visite), circa 1872 (Reel 5907, Frame 535-537)
    - F. D. Millet, circa 1910 (Reel 5907, Frame 538-539)
    - F. D. Millet in his studio with assistants, 1907 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Works of Art, circa 1897-1898, undated, 8.2:
    - Drawings by F. D. Millet, undated (Reel 5907, Frame 541-544)
    - Paintings by F. D. Millet, undated (Reel 5907, Frame 545-556)
    - Cartoons and Photographs from Puck Magazine by Other Artists (including images of F. D. Millet), circa 1897-1898 (Reel 5907, Frame 557-575)